[MUSIC]
[موسيقى]
In this module we're going to address a really important problem with machine
سنقوم اليوم في هذه الوحدة بتقديم مشكلة هامة بالفعل
learning today.
من سياق التعلم الآلي.
How to scale the algorithms we discussed to really large data sets.
كيفية قياس الخوارزميات التي ناقشناها لمجموعة كبيرة من البيانات.
The ideas we discuss today are going to be broadly applicable.
ستكون الأفكار التي نناقشها اليوم قابلة للتطبيق على نطاق واسع.
They're going to be applicable for all of classification.
وستكون قابلة للتطبيق على جميع التصنيفات.
They're also going to be applicable even for the regression course, or
وستكون قابلة للتطبيق حتى على الدورة التدريبية للانحدار،
the second course of the specialization.
أو الدورة التدريبية الثانية للتخصيص.
We're going to talk about the technique called stochastic gradient, and
وسنقوم بالحديث عن الأسلوب المسمى بالتدرج العشوائي،
when you relate it to something called online learning, where you're learning
عندما تقوم بربطه بما يسمى التعلم عبر الإنترنت،
from data streams where one piece of data is arriving at a time.
والتي تعلمتها من فيض البيانات والتي تصل فيه كل مجموعة بيانات على حدة.
Let's take a moment to review how gradient ascent works in the context of
ودعونا نستعرض كيفية عمل التدرج التصاعدي في سياق التصنيف،
classification, and how it's impacted by the data set size.
وكيف يتأثر بحجم مجموعة البيانات.
So we have a very large data set here, and
ولذا،فلدينا مجموعة بيانات كبيرة جدًا هنا،
we have a set of coefficients w(t) which we're hoping to update.
ولدينا مجموعة من المعاملات والتي نأمل بتحديثها.
So we're going to use gradient ascent.
لذا سنقوم باستخدام التدرج التصاعدي.
We're going to compute the gradient on this data set which requires us to make
وسنقوم بحساب التدرج على مجموعة البيانات هذه، والذي يتطلب منا القيام
a pass or scan over the data,
بالمرور عبر البيانات أو القيام بفحصها،
computing the contribution of each one of these data points to the gradient.
حساب الإسهامات لكلٍ من تلك نقاط البيانات بالنسبة للتدرج.
Then we compute the gradient, and we go ahead and update the parameters.
ومن ثم نحسب التدرج وبعد ذلك نقوم بتحديث المعلمات،
Then we get W (t+1).
ونحصل على (W (t+1.
Now we have to go back to data set, and make another pass where we visit every
ويجب علينا الآن العودة إلى مجموعة البيانات والقيام بمرور آخر
single data point, and we go computer a new gradient and
حيث قمنا بزيارة كل نقطة بيانات وحساب التدرج الجديد
update the parameters, the coefficients, and get W (t+2).
وتحديث المعلمات والمعاملات والحصول على (W (t+2.
So, in this process every time we're going to do a coefficient update
ولذا فإننا في هذه العملية في كل مرة نقوم فيها بتحديث المعاملات
we're going to have to make a full scan or a full pass over the entire data set,
يتوجب علينا القيام بفحص كامل أو مرور كامل من خلال مجموعة البيانات بالكامل،
which can be really slow if the data set is really big.
والتي تكون بطيئة بالفعل في حال كانت مجموعة البيانات كبيرة بالفعل.
And these days data sets are getting huge.
ومجموعات البيانات في الوقت الحالي تصبح أكبر.
You can think about the 4.8 billion webpages that are out there on the web.
يمكنك التفكر بأمر 4.8 مليارات صفحة ويب على مواقع الويب.
You can think about the fact that Twitter, for example,
ويمكنك استعراض تويتر على سبيل المثال،
is generating 500 million tweets a day.
حيث ينتج عنه ما يقارب من 500 مليون تغريدة في اليوم.
That's a lot.
وهذا كثير جدًا.
By the way follow me on Twitter.
وبالمناسبة، لا تنسى أن تتابعني على تويتر.
[LAUGH] Or you can think about again how the world is getting embedded with
(يضحك)ويمكنك أيضًا التأمل في كيف أن العالم ينغمس
sensors which is something we today call internet of things where you have
في المستشعرات والتي نسميها في أيامنا هذه إنترنت الأشياء
devices throughout the homes, devices we carry with us like the smart watch here.
والتي تغمر أجهزتها منازلنا، وكذلك الأجهزة التي نحملها مثل الساعة الذكية في سياق حديثنا هنا.
And everything else connected to each other generating tons and
وكل شيء يتصل ببعضه البعض والذي ينتج عنه
tons and tons of data.
مجموعات ومجموعات ومجموعات من البيانات.
And you can think about specific websites like YouTube where
ويمكنك التفكر في أمر مواقع محددة مثل YouTube،
300 hours of video uploaded every minute and nobody watches.
حيث يتم تحميل ما يقرب من 300 ساعة من مقاطع الفيديو كل دقيقة ولا يشاهدها أحد.
And this is a really fundamental problem for machine learning.
ويعد ذلك مشكلة أساسية للتعلم الآلي.
How to tackle this huge, massive data sets.
كيف يمكن تناول هذه المجموعات الضخمة والكبيرة من البيانات.
Let's use YouTube as an example.
دعونا نستخدم YouTube كمثال،
We have this tons of videos being uploaded,
لدينا هذا الحجم الضخم من مقاطع الفيديو التي تم تحميلها،
and there's a billion users who are visiting this website.
ولدينا كذلك مليارات من المستخدمين الذين يزورون موقع الويب هذا.
And YouTube makes money out of ad revenue or
ويجني YouTube أموالاً من عائد الإعلانات
showing the right ad to each one of it's users.
أو من عرض الإعلان الصحيح لكلٍ من مستخدميها.
Now, the number you should be thinking about is not 300 hours of video a minute
والآن، ليس عليك التفكر في 300 ساعة من مقاطع الفيديو التي يتم تم تحمليها في الدقيقة
or 1 billion users, but if you were thinking about the 4 billion page views or
أو 1 مليار من المستخدمين، ولكن التفكر في عدد 4 مليارات مشاهدات للصفحة
video views that they have everyday.
أو للفيديو والذي تحدث يوميًا.
So for each one of these page views they have to serve ads.
لذا عليهم تقديم إعلانات لكلٍ من مشاهدات الصفحة
They have to figure out what ads to put with those videos, and
وعليهم انتقاء أيٍ من الإعلانات تتناسب مع مقاطع الفيديو هذه،
they have to go back and retrain their learning algorithm.
لذا عليهم التمهل قليلاً وإعادة تنقيح خوارزمية التعلم الخاصة بهم.
In other words they need the machine and the algorithm to
وبصيغة أخرى، هم بحاجة إلى آلة وخوارزمية
figure out what ad to show that can deal with 5 billion events per day, and
لاكتشاف ما الإعلان الذي يجب عرضه لتناول 5 مليارات حدث في اليوم،
that's fast enough that you can make predictions as to what ad
وهذا سريع بما يكفي للتنبؤ بالإعلان
to show within milliseconds as you're going to watch those videos.
الذي يتم عرضه ضمن جزء من ألف جزء من الثانية، في حين تقوم بمشاهدة مقاطع الفيديو هذه.
[MUSIC]
[موسيقى]